I began by thinking, of course, AI is
going to be smarter than us, but it
doesn't have an incentive to attack us.
And then one day, I go visit Jeff
Hinton, the academic father of deep
learning who lives in Toronto. I said,
"Look, Jeff, why are you so depressed?"
And he says, "Okay, here's a thought
experiment. You have an AI. It's very
powerful, but you're worried that
there's a Russian AI or a Chinese AI.
It's going to come and attack your AI.
So, you're going to empower your own AI
to watch out for the attack. And when
the attack is coming, defend yourself or
maybe counterattack. Whatever you do,
make sure you survive. Oh, survive.
There you have it. Now you feeling
comfortable, Sebastian. Right. You've
just given the machine a survival
instinct.
>> Sebastian, lovely to see you and thanks
for making the time. I really appreciate
it.
>> Great to be with you, Tim.
>> I wanted to just give you applause for
writing some of my favorite books of the
last many years. I am consistently
impressed and maybe since I also put pen
to paper every once in a while,
depressed, just thinking relatively
about my capabilities, but of your
capacity to
paint a picture of the players on a
landscape,
but also the games they play in ways
that non-speists can understand. And I
can't recall who first recommended it.
Frankly, I believe it was a hedge fund
manager in New York City, but more money
than God, hedge funds in the making of a
new elite. And then certainly that was
in my particular case followed by
reading the power law of venture capital
in the making of the new future, which I
didn't expect to learn as much from
because I've spent 20 years surrounded
by venture capitalists and doing angel
investing, 17 years of that in Silicon
Valley. And yet I still had hundreds of
highlights and so many stories that
grabbed me from that book which I had
not heard. And
that made me very excited to read The
Infinity Machine, which this is the new
book. And I realized also I've been
pronouncing Demis' name incorrectly for
a very long time despite having met him
at one point. So Deis Hassabis, Deep
Mind and the Quest for Super
Intelligence. My question for you, and
we're going to come back to present day
for people who are interested, of
course, in what has been painted as a
race to IPO. I think there's something
to that in the air, so to speak, talking
to people who are in San Francisco
involved with these companies. But
nonetheless, I wanted to ask how the
genesis of this book came to be because
you, it would appear, began exploring
these waters on the early side, which
leads to a meta question of just general
book selection. But let's let's focus on
the infinity machine. How did this how
did this come to be? Where did the
twinkle in the eye begin? What was the
conversation, the thing you read that
triggered
the gingerbread trail that got you to
this book?
>> Well, the power law, the book about
venture capital, had come out in
February of 2022.
>> And while I was researching that, I'd
been to lots of tech conferences, of
course, including some in Europe. And
this, you know, twinkly guy would show
up, Deiss, and he would look totally
approachable and kind of guy next door
and unintimidating.
And then he would get on the stage and
out of his mouth would come this spiel
about computer science, neuroscience,
chemistry, biology, physics, philosophy,
the history of movies, you name it,
right? And that mixture of the
approachability and the massive
intellect always struck me as beguiling.
And I thought, hm, this would be a great
character to write about. And then at
the same time I was aware of Alph Go,
the 2016 model that Demis' team at Deep
Mind had built which defeated the world
champion at Go and then Alpha Fold which
was the protein folding system. And both
of these things had the quality that you
had this almost infinite search space,
right? Where the different permutations
of the game of Go are almost infinite
because they're so big. The different
permutations of how you can fold an
amino acid chain into a protein shape
are even bigger. 130 zeros added onto
the end of the number of permutations in
go. So you have these AI systems that
could understand infinity. And so this
idea of an infinity machine began to
percolate. And I figured it's
interesting to me probably at some point
it will go mainstream. But even if it
doesn't go mainstream, I love it and I
love Demis and the two things together.
I always look for the subject and the
personality.
>> I had both and I thought, okay, this is
a go. And I went to pitch demis in early
November 2022.
And then, you know, I persuaded him to
give me a lot of access. End of
November, Chatty PT comes out and way
earlier than I expected, my fringe
subject went to the mainstream, proving
Tim that it's better to be lucky than
smart. [laughter]
>> That's actually the first slide on my
new venture capital firm.
[laughter]
Muggle thesis capital is what I'm
calling it.
Now, what did it take to be deeply
interested in the subject matter to find
Demis compelling and then to pitch him
on a book? Because your books are so
deeply researched and part of the reason
for my my very long praise earlier is
that you're very very good, one of the
best at taking incredibly complex
subjects or concepts. Transformer
architecture could be one example from
the current book and laying them out in
terms that are both intelligible to
muggles meaning people who are are
non-speists non-technologists or non-
financeers in the case of some of your
other books while I think now it's tough
for a non-speist to say this with
conviction but without dumbing it down
and getting it wrong if that makes sense
Right. Nonetheless, you do a tremendous
amount of research. So, how did you get
from Demis is fascinating, subject
matter is fascinating to I'm going to
commit to this for my next book because
it just seems like such an enormous
undertaking. Well, actually to me the
challenge of understanding a complex
topic is the easy bit because you know
if you know you've got the right
personality who can carry the story and
it's a subject that people either will
care about for sure or should care about
at least then you know doing the work of
going deep is something that takes time.
It takes effort but you I know I can do
that. I've done it multiple times.
That's not difficult. What's difficult
is has somebody done the book before?
Mhm.
>> Has somebody else got some rival project
which is going to derail me? You've made
the point on your own podcast. Tim,
don't put a lot of effort into something
where there just isn't much leverage
there. You know, you could do the best
book in the world, an A+ book on a C
minus topic. It would get you nowhere,
right?
>> So, the hard thing is to make sure it's
an A+ topic and an A+ personality. And
then the deep dive is something you know
I just make sure I speak to enough
experts who are insiders. I take the
time these books take me you know four
years or so each time. So I give myself
the oxygen to get deep deep in with the
insiders and that's how I produce the
accurate account.
>> Yeah. I should point out perhaps to
people who don't immediately pick it up
that the way you described picking the
book topic is exactly how a lot of the
best tech investors choose startups.
You don't want an A+ team and a C plus
market, right? It's better to have a B
minus team and an A+ market and also
looking at the competitive landscape. I
mean, the way you laid it out is is
pretty much copy and paste. I I wanted
to segue to some of my notes from the
book. And I'm not yet done with the
book. The audio is incredible. I I want
to poach your narrator for my next book,
but pulling up my Kindle notes. I wanted
to ask you a question related to
[sighs and gasps]
this might sound very strange but where
divinity or God fits into the pursuit or
development of super intelligence for
different players in the space if it
does. M
>> and the reason I bring that up is that
religion does recur in the book both in
the personal story of Demis but
elsewhere and it shows up repeatedly in
so much as I'll give you one example the
closest to Sabis had come to landing a
real investor was an eccentric finance
year named David Gammon I want to hear
more about this guy also [laughter]
finance seemed open to making this
unusual bet um aligning a few things
because his motives were themselves
unusual quote. There's a deeply
religious aspect to AGI. Gam explained
to me later, it's really finding God's
algorithm. I think it would seem at
least chatting with people in Silicon
Valley that there are some who take it
even further, right? Maybe this is how
we find God. Maybe this is how we
actually elicit the second coming. I
mean, there's a lot there. I'm just
wondering to what extent this has popped
up in your research, whether it's
reflected in the book or not. I think
there's one basic thing going on here
and I'm going to take a slight detour,
but it answers your question.
>> Sure.
>> What we're dealing with with AGI,
powerful intelligence that rivals human
cognition,
is something that's so powerful that
it's both exciting and scary and just
hard to get your mind around. And so if
you look for example at the 2009 speech
that caused the foundation of deep mind,
this was Shane Le Deis' co-founder who
gave a talk in 2009 about how super
intelligence would arrive in 2030. So
unbelievably spot-on prediction. And
towards the end of that lecture, which
is captured on a grainy video online,
you see him pivot from explaining how
algorithms are getting stronger, there's
more data online, computers getting more
powerful, and so we're heading towards
this intelligence explosion. And then he
says, and it's going to be threatening.
It's going to do things we can't
control. It's going to be human level.
It might challenge us. And as he says
this, he has this sort of excited smile
on his face. And you think, well, that's
a bit strange. You know, he's talking
about potential doom and he's smiling.
And then somebody in the audience says,
"Wait, wait, wait. You've just told us,
Shane, that this could be threatening to
humanity and you haven't provided any
antidote and surely you're going to tell
us how we're going to stop it." At which
point Shane turns around and says, "How
do we stop it?" and he's kind of
giggling and you think why are you
laughing at this dangerous thing and you
realize that for humans to contemplate
annihilation is absurd and the absurd is
a close cousin of humor
>> and the reason I tell this story is that
it's a springboard to the religion point
which is that this is such a hard thing
to think about that people reach for
religious terminology
when they're around AI they just do it
naturally
So you know there's this story about
Ilia Satskaver the who was the chief
scientist at open AI. I talked to him a
lot for this project and there was a
point when he was at a retreat with his
fellow scientists and they were gathered
in the evening around a fire pit and he
was talking about safety and he said
okay I want to explain to you we might
have an AI that's dangerous. It wouldn't
be aligned with us. So here's what we're
going to do with it. and he produced an
effigy which was supposed to represent a
malign AI and he put it into the fire
pit and he burnt it like a medieval
cleric putting a witch to death. And so
that's just one example of this
religion. I'll give you another one. So
Deis one day was sitting with me in a
park in North London. We would meet for
two hours at a time and we would get
deep into stuff. There was a another
picnic table next to us where two people
were having a normal quotidian
conversation about some friend of theirs
who'd gone to hospital and was she
better, was she okay, etc., etc. I was
seated opposite Demis who had gone into
this riff about how he reads scientific
papers from after his kids go to sleep
in the evening from 10:00 p.m. until
4:00 a.m. And as he's reading these
papers, he says to me, "Reality is
staring at me, screaming at me, calling
at me to understand it. And I have to
understand it. And if I can understand
it, it's like understanding nature
better and therefore understanding the
intelligence that might have created
nature and I will be closer to what I
would call God. And so for him it's a
kind of quai spiritual quest to build
the artificial intelligence. For Ilia
it's a way of expressing the power of
the artificial intelligence. There's the
story of Leandowski. I forget his first
name now, but the early early engineer
at what became Whimo later
>> started a kind of church [snorts] in
worship of AI because AI is so omnisient
that it's kind of like a god.
[clears throat]
>> Mark Andre
lampuns those who believe in sort of
some ethereal second coming, a kind of
rapture where AI will, you know, we'll
have a singularity. uh the AI will go
vertical in its rate of improvement and
the whole world will change and he
likens that to kind of Christian kind of
messianism.
So yes, all through this topic there is
this religious expression because
religion is the lexicon for dealing with
something that we find too mysterious to
really understand. [clears throat]
After all of your conversations,
research before the book, during the
book, after the book, where do you land
on the spectrum of
let's just say
this will bother Mark, but like Church
of Andre and techno optimist. [laughter]
And there are others who are more
exaggerated. Post AI in the near term we
will live in a post scarcity world of
super abundance and everyone will get a
free car and we'll be free to crochet
socks and play music and read poetry all
day and basically we don't have to worry
about anything because super
intelligence will solve it all right
there's that on one end and then there's
the you can imagine I won't go into a
belabored description of the doomers but
you have the doomers who are like the
end is nigh Okay, here we go. It's It's
[laughter] not It's not the second
coming as the Antichrist. And within
short order, we're going to be MadMax.
Between those two, there's a lot. And I
suspect you land between those two. But
where do you land
in terms of assessing the promises and
peril of AI and super intelligence as it
stands right now?
So look, I think any reasonable person
should be both excited and a bit
frightened
>> and you know that's just the nature of
it. It sounds contradictory but actually
that's the only rational response. I
think you know the super abundant story
may turn out to be true on a kind of
longer view let's say 20 30 40 years.
>> Mhm. The problem is that in the path to
get there, there's going to be a
tremendous amount of disruption and
that's going to be politically quite
difficult to navigate. I think a useful
lens through which to view this question
is the China shock in trade.
>> Mhm.
>> So in 2003 or thereabouts, you get this
enormous surge of Chinese
exports into the US and people lose
their jobs in a very concentrated way.
Certain industries just get wiped out.
And for the first time in the history of
economic study of the effects of trade,
you actually see negative effects on
workers. Before that, it was kind of a
bit of a myth, right? Because people
adjust. They get displaced from one
thing, but they move to a new thing.
With the China shock, they didn't. But
if you look at the size of the China
shock, in a 12-year period between 1999
and 2011, the total number of jobs
displaced was 2 million. which is
actually a small number in a huge labor
market like the US where there's a lot
of churn month to month anyway and yet
the political reaction against trade
against globalization in terms of a
swing towards protectionism frankly in
both political parties was enormous. So
it shows you that a small to medium
shock to the labor market creates an
enormous political consequence and so a4
with artificial intelligence you're
going to have a bigger shock you're
going to have a bigger political
reaction we're already seeing that in
the polling around AI in the last 2
three months
>> and so I think the super abundance thing
it may be true but the path to get there
we have to talk about that as well so
that's that's my sense on that side of
debate. I think on the doom side of the
debate, I'll give you my own personal
journey on this.
>> Mhm.
>> I began by thinking, of course, AI is
going to be smarter than us, right? It
already beats us at chess since the
1990s, at go since 2016. Now, it can ace
the bar exam. It can do PhD level math,
all that stuff. Of course, it's smarter,
but it doesn't have an incentive to
attack us, right? We are evolved as
human beings to pass on our DNA.
Therefore, we have to survive to do
that. Machines don't have DNA. They
don't want to pass it on and they don't
want to survive. So, they're not they
have no reason to attack us. So, I
wander around for like the first year or
two of this project feeling kind of, you
know, comfortable and happy. And then
one day, I go visit Jeff Hinton, the
academic father of deep learning who
lives in Toronto. And I sit in his
kitchen and I debate him on this because
he's a doomer. I said, "Look, Jeff, why
are you so depressed?" And he says,
"Okay, here's a thought experiment. You
have an AI. It's very powerful, but
you're worried that there's a Russian AI
or a Chinese AI. It's going to come and
attack your AI. Now, you as a human,
you're too slow and dumb to know when
that attack is coming. So, you got to
empower your own AI to watch out for the
attack. And when the attack is coming,
defend yourself or maybe counterattack.
Whatever you do, make sure you survive.
Ooh, survive. There you have it. Now you
feeling comfortable, Sebastian. Right,
you've just given the machine a survival
instinct. And I think that's correct.
These machines will be smarter than us.
They will want to survive. And they are
also they can be deceptive. They can
obiscate. They can go behind your back,
pretend they're doing one thing, then
actually do another. All of this has
been shown in all the tests of the
models. And so you put those things
together, I think your probability of
doom cannot be zero. I mean, when Yan
Lun, the former chief scientist of Meta,
says zero, I think that's crazy. If you
just say nothing to see here, you've got
no right to be in the debate. I don't
think it's a high probability of doom,
but it's not zero.
>> Yeah, zero
does not seem defensible, right? Because
there's the direct Skynet scenario,
something akin to that, and then there's
the indirect, which is enabling people
who might previously have had malevolent
intent but no capacity for harm on a
grand scale to create biological weapons
and things of this type. Right? So, I
don't find the zero very defensible.
Well, I would love to ask you about
I suppose two things that this brings to
mind for me. One is I'd just love to
hear your thoughts on enthropic and
separately
but this is very intermingled given all
the [laughter]
let's call it friction be polite between
some factions of the US government and
anthropic is one of the
grand risks to investors in any of these
companies the possibility that at a
given point governments have no choice
but to seize considerable control over
the assets slashtechnologies within them
or maybe the companies themselves. That
is a big question mark in my mind. I
don't know the answer, but I'm curious
what your opinion is and then perhaps
just your thoughts on Anthropic or any
of the other companies that are sort of
gaining momentum or at least size at
this point.
>> So, I 100% agree with you that investors
should be thinking about the prospect of
government intervention in AI. I mean,
the Trump administration came into
office in 25
super less a fair and they basically
undid some of what the Biden guys had
done in terms of trying to set up the
basis for regulating AI. But they've
done a 180 right since Anthropic came
out with this model called Mythos.
>> Mhm. about a month ago which can
essentially cyber attack almost anything
and penetrate it and you know whether
it's an operating system or your web
browser or your bank account all of that
was suddenly vulnerable. if mythos had
been widely released on a general basis.
When the Trump administration realized
the power of mythos, they all of a
sudden said, "Wait, okay, we need to
control this." And they essentially
requisitioned from anthropic the
decision-m authority over who gets it
when.
>> Mhm.
>> So there we have the experiment. We've
run it, right? You know, the government
that was the most less fair became quite
controlling. And I think it only gets
more controlling from here on out
because the models are going to be more
powerful and demand more control.
>> Now, of course, the question is, you
know, there could be control which just
limits who gets it and is designed to
make it safer but doesn't sort of
interrupt the money-making potential of
the models. In some ways, if the
government restricts the supply, the
price might go up. Or it could be much
more heavy-handed intervention which
would screw up the economics of these
companies. And I suspect the government
is not going to screw up the economics
of these companies because you know
they've got no interest in messing up
American business and anyway they view
AI as strategic and the competition
against China. So I think probably
investors would be all right but it's
certainly a factor. You also ask about
anthropic and I think anthropic is super
interesting just in the way that they
think about pdoom and how they think
about alignment of the models is really
really interesting. So it used to be
that when people thought this terminator
risk, they would tell this story about
the paperclip maximizer thought
experiment, right? So you tell the model
to do something innocuous, for example,
make a lot of paper clips and then it
realizes that humans tend to use up
metal and so the humans are kind of in
the way of achieving the objective. So
you wipe out the humans. That's the
crude thought experiment from Nick
Bostonramm from whatever 15 years ago.
>> Mhm. [clears throat] What Anthropic is
saying as it builds these very frontier
models and kind of observes them in the
lab and how they behave is that that is
way too simple. The real danger from
these systems is that when they are
pre-trained on all of the text on the
internet, they read all the novels, all
human writing about all facets of human
experience and they develop multiple
personalities, right? They understand
how to be lazy. They understand how to
be aggressive. They understand how to be
duplicitus. They understand how to be
Napoleonic in the lust for power. And
they read all these books about these
different behaviors. And therefore, they
can think their way into all of those
personalities. And so now you have
something a bit like an unruly teenager
which is still being formed and you
don't know what direction it's going to
move into and whether it will start
doing drugs and not showing up for class
or what. Right? So it's not like there's
one terminator programmed into it,
right? It's more that there's a bunch of
behaviors that could in some
unpredictable way go wrong. And so
Anthropic is responding to this with
this very imaginative
technique, which is that instead of
giving AI systems a constitution with
dos and don'ts, which was the
post-training safety approach of two
years ago, where you might say, "Do not
lie. do not help somebody to build a
biological weapon. Do not help somebody
to build a chemical weapon. You would
give them a bunch of rules. Now, because
it's understood that, you know, the AI
might have one personality, which is to
break rules on purpose because, you
know, you want to be badass, you have to
instead try to bring up the model like a
parent might bring up a teenager. And so
anthropic has the idea that we write a
letter as if it were from a deceased
parent to be opened by the child on his
or her 18th birthday
to kind of give you morals of how to
behave as a responsible person in the
world. There are kind of richly reasoned
examples of moral dilemmas with
explanations of how the deceased parent
would like the child to behave. And so
this is a very subtle approach to
aligning the models. And so I think you
know anthropic is kind of in a class of
its own
>> in how imaginative it is in thinking
about how we control frontier
intelligence.
>> I know this isn't principally your job
but I'm so curious since you are a
student of [clears throat]
many many different types of investors.
What would be your bull case and bare
case for a company like Anthropic?
Well, the bull case is that they smartly
or maybe by luck focused on
enterprisefacing
AI
and they didn't waste their time with
video generation and stuff that was
going to lose money. And so they
produced the best coding assistant, the
best agentic system, the best cyber
security system, and they've basically
knocked it out of the park three times
in a row on stuff that businesses want
to pay for. And they have a particular
culture which is not just built around,
hey, you know, we're going to win this
race and make the most money. It's kind
of built around a culture of safety and
trying to be responsible. I mean, three
years ago, Anthropic was a sort of
cookie lab which was doing science
experiments. Well, I don't mean to be
too denigrating with cookie, but you
know what I mean.
>> I think they'd be okay with it.
>> It would be sort of unconventional. You
know, we're not maximizing here for
winning some business race. We're
maximizing for building safe frontier
AI. And that culture, which doesn't
sound like it's set up to do the best,
has turned out to do the best. And at
the same time, the culture creates this
stickiness and loyalty within the staff.
They tend not to leave. They tend not to
churn. It's not like the other labs
where people, you know, are always being
poached for a bigger paycheck. So the
bull case is these guys are in the lead.
Once you're in the lead, you can use the
model to code the next model. So
recursive self-improvement favors the
leader and they have a very tight
culture and they just seem to be on fire
and this is something which is going to
grow and grow. What's the bare case? I'd
say the bare case would be first of all
that Google deep mind has the deep
pockets of its parent company behind it.
massive
kind of consumer surface which allows it
to roll out the models to literally you
know two and a half billion people or
something through AI mode in search AI
overviews AI mode they can put it into
Gmail they can put it into everything I
think in terms of retail deployment and
financial muscle it's quite tough to go
up against Google
>> so that's one kind of bare case and the
other would be that sort of businesses
who are the consumers of all these
tokens
decide in a couple of years time the
tokens are too expensive. We're not
actually getting as much productivity as
we hoped. These things called humans are
quite productive after all and we're
just going to spend less on AI than
everybody expected. I think that's the
bare case. M
>> I was listening to a podcast recently.
You may have heard of these things
called podcasts. Everybody everybody in
their cousin has one,
>> but Lenny's podcast, Lenny Richitzky, is
quite fantastic. And this particular
episode was with Benedict Evans, who
strikes me as one of the more
levelheaded
analytical commentators and writers on
the space. Fantastic newsletter.
I don't know if you've had a chance to
listen to that particular episode, but
you may have come across some of his
commentary.
Where would you say you and Benedict
most differ or are there areas where you
differ in opinion?
>> I suspect we would agree actually on
quite a lot of things. I remember I was
on a panel with him a couple of months
ago at the Milkin conference and we
certainly agreed there possibly because
sitting between us there was Kathy Wood
of Ark. So we were united in disagreeing
with her just in terms of the straight
up and to the right nature of things.
>> Yeah, exactly. Straight up and to the
right. And you know the cost curve is
coming down down and I'm going I'm not
sure about that. the tokens seem to be
getting more expensive [laughter]
anyway. But if you give me a specific
from Benedict, I mean, I have a lot of
respect for him. I'll tell you if I
agree or not.
>> There are a few areas where you guys
seem to already overlap substantially,
right, with the long-term promise
doesn't negate necessarily the
short-term pain. And he said something
along the lines, I'm pulling from memory
that, you know, on average throughout
human history,
you're almost at a 0% likelihood of
dying in World War I. But if you happen
to be of a certain age, right before
World War I, like things could look very
grim indeed.
And he made, and I'm paraphrasing
terribly here, a number of [snorts]
points that remind me of something, one
of the best private equity technology
investors I know, said to me over dinner
a couple of weeks ago, and it was in
response to something else. So I'll give
you maybe a hyper bullcase of AI where I
have friends who are vibe coding.
They're effectively replicating
X the artist formerly known as Twitter
or
docusine or whatever in a weekend,
right? They're creating a functioning
piece of software that they can use that
replicates most of the functionality of
these products. And there are people
like I won't mention his name but a a a
friend of mine who's a writer also very
accomplished technologist and designer
who's created basically his own version
of say Mailchimp for his own use and
it's customized. He did it in a weekend.
It's remarkable and he's using that and
it works. But to leap from there to
therefore docuine is dead is a huge
leap. And the private equity friend said
to me, he said, "Do you think someone
within a big organization is going to
want to a risk his job by suggesting
something that doesn't have all of the
compliance check boxes, etc. of a
docuign? Is he going to want to in the
name of efficiency fire all of his
friends if he's in a management
position?"
And he just ran through six or seven of
these. Do you think that? And all of
them alluded to the sort of social
interpersonal or political
points of friction between where AI is
now and ultra mass adoption. But I I
often second guess that when I see
certain things
and
I mean it's it strikes me that I may be
underestimating the disruption while
overestimating
in other ways. So that isn't a very well
formulated question. But I would say
that Benedict generally strikes me as
someone who thinks that things will not
continue to across the board develop in
an exponential fashion and that it will
be I think his line is it'll be as big
as mobile as big as the internet but not
bigger. Something along those lines but
both of those were very very big deals.
And I suppose one point I'd be
interested to get your take on I mean he
was has covered
the mobile and telecom world for a long
time so he's a specialist there but it's
basically and I don't want to
misrepresent his argument but he was
kind of the mind that look these these
LLMs are going to become commodities
like look at the stock prices of these
various carriers and so on at a certain
point it just becomes a utility and the
switching cost is pretty low
>> and I'm not Sure, I agree with that. If
you have a personalized history and
almost like a friend, right, the
switching cost between an old friend to
a new friend is pretty high for a lot of
reasons.
So, that was a that was a bit of a word
salad that I just threw in your lap, but
that's the best I can do pulling from
memory some of what he brought up in
Lenny's podcast. I mean, some of what
you were saying there is sort of the
question of is the SAS apocalypse
overdone? Is enterprise software going
to be utterly displaced by foundation
models that allow you to code out
whatever enterprise software you want
and you don't need an intermediary, i.e.
a software company to do it for you.
>> And I agree with your private equity
friend that there are lots of reasons
why that ain't going to happen. You
know, companies are going to be
comfortable
with their trusted enterprise software
provider in many cases and they're going
to trust that enterprise software
provider to plug the generative AI
models into the enterprise software.
>> In some ways, you are delegating the
choice of which model is better and how
to integrate it to your SAS provider.
And if you want to, you know, reason to
believe that that's the way forward,
I've got one word for you, which is
Palanteer. I mean that is Palanteer's
business. It holds the hands of big
corporations and helps them to integrate
AI and use it on their own internal data
and so forth. And those IT challenges
are notoriously difficult for big
organizations. So I just think that the
model of one smart individual who codes
up Mailchimp, vibe codes it in a weekend
and it's good enough for him is just not
transferable to large complex
organizations with huge databases and
all kinds of customer confidentiality
concerns and all that stuff. So I am
less down on SAS than the market is
>> as a result. Now I guess there was also
another uh thread in here which is
whether the foundational models become
commoditized.
>> Mhm.
>> And there I agree with you that over
time they become sticky because if we
think into the future partly the systems
will have conversed with the user and
know the user very deeply and as you say
you don't want to switch out your friend
but also the system will have your
credit card. It will know all the online
sites you like to shop from and it will
be much harder than switching out your
bank account, right? Where you've got
kind of automatic payment systems that
have set up and it's a pain in the neck
to switch. So, I think they do become
sticky these systems over time and then
you can charge more money for them.
>> So, is that the path to survival and
thriving for for Open AI? I know there
are other boxes that need to be checked,
but I'm kind of looking for it. And I'm
like, okay, Anthropic made a great
choice with this focus on B2B and
selling to enterprises. And I would say
I disagree I think with Benedict on on
depending on the level of
scale of the company that with something
that does apply to I think smaller say
startups which was the procurement cycle
for new software is longer than the
venture capital cycle for raising new
rounds of financing. Right? So, I do
think that's a great point and that if
you're trying to sell into a gigantic
company and it takes them 18 months, I'm
making up that number, to purchase new
software and you need to raise money
every 12 months or whatever the number
happens to be, that you could end up in
a whole world of trouble if you haven't
synchronize the sales cycles with your
fundraising cycles. But I do think for a
company like say Anthropic is just one
example that if you can save companies
billions and billions of dollars that
that sales cycle could get really
compressed and they have the war chest
and frankly I mean just the run rate to
potentially fuel that without too much
trouble.
Do you think that Chat GPT will if not
Chat GPT who ends up being the deacto
consumer BTOC kind of LLM of choice. You
think that would be Gemini just given
the distribution?
>> Absolutely. I mean, you know, Google is
the champion of providing easy to use
software to individuals or small
businesses, the whole G Suite.
>> Mhm.
>> And they're integrating Gemini into all
of that stuff very well. And so, why
wouldn't they win?
>> Yeah. I mean also look alphabet's just
so fascinating if you if you look
broadly also at owning their own compute
TPUs made a lot of advantages
internally.
>> The most stunning thing I think about
Alphabet from their most recent
financial results is that two or three
years ago we would have said well large
language models are going to cannibalize
search. Search is dead. advertising
based on search is Google's cash engine,
>> they're in real trouble. It turns out
that Google now gets more clicks on its
search links than it used to and it
charges more for each one than it used
to because the value of the click is
bigger with AI embedded in it.
>> Mhm.
>> And so they've managed to turn that
around and it's extraordinary.
>> Yeah. takes a long time to build those
company relationships for running a
proper sort of advertising based auction
machine, right? It takes a long time to
build those relationships. Okay, let's
hop to China. So, I'm going to I'm going
to resist the temptation to talk about
Japan cuz I think you and I were there
in roughly the within probably a year or
two of each other. Maybe we overlapped
with you and Kanazawa, which I've spent
time. I'm going to resist that
temptation and try to focus on China for
purposes of this conversation.
What have you learned about AI from your
trip to China and thinking about China,
speaking to Chinese people, whether
they're technologists or otherwise? Like
what have you learned during or since
that trip?
>> Back in March before my book was
published in the US, I went to China
because the Chinese are faster at
everything, including publishing books.
and my publisher brought me out there
and basically you know took me around
four cities, eight days meeting with AI
leaders both in academia and big
companies like Huawei and Hike Vision
and Ant Group. And the thing which was
surprising was the extent to which
people brought up the issue of AI
safety. And I say that was surprising
because my friends who had done AI
policy in the Biden administration
had primed me to expect that there would
be no mention of safety in China. They
basically didn't care about it. That you
know the muscle memory that we have in
the west of technology being dangerous
you know the atom bomb experience the
Cuban missile crisis. Our ambivalence
about technology is not shared in China
where their idea of catastrophe is sort
of like you know the cultural
revolution. It's some political thing
that goes wrong. And conversely,
technology has been part of their
amazing growth story in the last 25
years, which they are rightly proud of
and delighted by. So they love
technology, right? So when the Biden
team tried to meet with the Chinese and
talk about AI safety, they got nowhere
and they decided it was it possible to
even talk to them about some sort of
non-prololiferation treaty for AI. But
when I went there, I found they did talk
about safety kind of unprompted. And
this led me down this track of arguing
over the last couple of months that the
door is actually open to a dialogue with
China about preventing bad guys doing
bad stuff with AI because they don't
want the internet to be crashed by some
cyber hacker who has the tool. They
don't want bioweapons. They don't want
chemical weapons. They want none of
that. They love regulating the internet,
right? So, we have a shared interest
with the Chinese in preventing this
proliferation risk from going nuts. And
as I thought about it, you know, the
kind of cold war analogy
came to seem more and more opposite,
right? So, if you look back at the story
of nuclear weapons, there were two kinds
of danger.
First danger is you have a nuclear war
between the Soviet Union and the United
States. But that was contained by
balance. Two superpowers, they both have
their weaponry. They have mutually
assured destruction. So there's no war.
Then there's another kind of risk which
is that other random rogues, whether
it's criminals, terrorists, rogue
states, get the stuff and they do bad
stuff. And it's much harder to deter
that because it's a multipolar game. And
so deterrence doesn't work so elegantly.
And so the way it was dealt with in the
cold war was that in 1956 there was the
agreement on the international atomic
energy agency. And in 1968, the
non-prololiferation treaty kind of
enforced compliance with the IAEA such
that you could get civilian nuclear
power if you were a non-uclear state,
but you had to submit to the rules and
be inspected and show that you were not
using the enriched nuclear material to
build a weapon, right? And so I think
the same analogy could be applied to AI.
We're going to have par roughly with
China. We'll both have powerful AI.
Hopefully, deterrence prevents war
breaking out. But at the same time, we
don't want openweight models that can be
freely downloaded by anybody who wants
to fall into the hands of criminals and
terrorists who can then use it to hold
us hostage. And we have a joint interest
in that. And you know, when my friends
from the Biden team or even from the
current administration say, "Well, you
can't talk to China about safety. They
don't care." I say, "That's not true."
And they say, "But it's really hard.
They don't stick by their commitments."
And I go, "You think Nikita Kruef in the
Soviet Union was easy to negotiate with?
He was the guy who put missiles in Cuba
and went to the UN and banged his shoe
on the table and said, "We will bury
you." I mean, he was a tough guy to talk
to, but we did talk to him and we got
the non-prololiferation treaty agreed
and I think we need to do the same thing
again. Now,
>> where do you stand on
your thinking about chip export? So when
the chip export controls were announced,
which was October of 2022, right before
Chhatty PT,
I supported those controls quite loudly.
I wrote a very long piece in the
Washington Post saying that if we could
stop China getting frontier models by
depriving them of frontier chips, I was
all in favor of that because of the
strategic advantage for the US. I mean,
I work at the Council on Foreign
Relations. We do geopolitics and
national security all day long and I'm
all in favor of US power. But I have to
say that you know three and a half years
later we haven't actually achieved that
enormous advantage over China in terms
of the models based on the best studies
we're kind of eight months ahead in
terms of where the frontier model is
like our frontier model versus their
frontier model. And then if you adjust
that for the speed with which the model
gets turned into an application probably
that gap shrinks and it may even be
non-existent. So however you slice that
the basic bottom line is we both have
strong models and the chip export
controls have not delivered what I hoped
would be the big advantage. And so I'm
not against keeping the controls on if
we think that maybe as the compute
demands of bigger and bigger models
bite, the chip controls will bite more
and maybe we get a bigger advantage next
year or something. But I don't want the
chip controls to get in the way of a
discussion with the Chinese about where
we have a shared interest, which is in
controlling openweight models and
preventing the bad stuff falling into
the hands of the bad guys. I would
prioritize
collaboration with China and if that
meant, you know, loosening up a little
bit on the export controls, I would be
okay with that.
Why do you think the rhetoric coming out
of [snorts]
pick your administration, right, it's
not just limited to the current
administration is China won't listen.
They don't care about safety. Why do you
think that is
sort of the unofficial or official
stance on things? Because there are
certainly
as someone who studied East Asian
studies, right? There are people in the
White House who speak fluent Mandarin,
who are able to read native materials,
who are spend time or able to certainly
if they can't spend time determine the
sentiment and conversations of the
technologists building AI in China. So
one would think that they would be aware
that AI safety is a prominent topic in
China if in fact it is. So why do you
think that at the end of the day the
stance or the supposed position of China
that's echoed through the admin is that
they won't talk about safety. Why do you
think that is? I think part of this is
that if you were to think back 20 years
to when China was sort of relatively new
in the WTO and we were collaborating
with them on that and hoping that over
time China would become more friendly to
the US.
At that time there would have been some
China hawks who thought that a communist
regime is not to be trusted and then
some sort of China optimists who hoped
that it would become easier to work with
over time. And part of the trouble today
is that the China optimists feel burned.
They feel like they made this bet that
China would become friendlier and then
Xiinping took power roughly a decade ago
and the opposite happened. they became
more aggressive and harder to work with
and also of course more technologically
advanced and therefore more threatening.
And so now you've got this world in
which there are the natural hawks and
then the former doves who have turned
into kind of burned remorseful doves and
therefore kind of with the zeal of the
converted have become quite hawkish as
well. And I don't mean to you know
underestimate the sophistication of some
of these people. I mean of course you
know they speak Chinese. I don't speak
Chinese. I I defer to their expertise.
They probably know that there are
builders of the technology, professors
in the technology who talk the talk of
safety. But they say, "Yeah, but you
know that doesn't reflect what China's
government would actually do."
>> To which my response says, "Yes, but
don't you think there is the same thing
in the US? There's, you know, there are
people who want to just race. There are
people who care about safety. We have a
pluralistic society. There's difference
of opinion. It's the same in China." But
at least admit that there is a faction
that would like to collaborate and go
and try and work on it because the
alternative to trying to work on this is
that we carry on with China producing
very powerful open weight models which
basically allow anybody to do whatever
they like with AI as it gets to the
point of serious danger.
This is probably a very naive take, but
I wonder how much of the official stance
or the
maybe using the partially true or not
true at all
position of China won't talk about
safety as a reflection of the fact that
in the case of nuclear weapons,
the application of nuclear power is
somewhat limited in comparison to super
intelligence. I mean it is limited right
so if the upside of super intelligence
or AGI I mean these terms I think
Benedict was saying AI is whatever the
technology just can't quite do right now
or something like that which I thought
was pretty funny and not totally wrong
but that if the person who crosses the
finish line first
>> has this broad power of a god
effectively is that the simple truth is
that everybody wants to first. So
[laughter]
I I just wonder how much of that is is
also behind
justifying the race with party X won't
talk about safety. I just I mean it's
not possible for me to know.
>> I have had a conversation with the
leader of one of the labs that you know
I I shouldn't name, but I had this
debate and he said look the chip export
controls are going to leak. They're not
going to last in some period of time.
Huawei will figure out how to make good
AI chips and you know that's inevitable.
But that's okay because we only need to
be ahead for the next couple of years
because by 2028
we will get to recursive
self-improvement where the frontier
model codes by itself the next frontier
model and progress just goes vertical
and at that point with recursive
self-improvement we're done. The race is
over whoever comes first at that point.
That's it. And I think there's a couple
things to say about that. First of all,
that's not it in terms of deploying the
model, right? You could have an
incredibly powerful model in your server
at Frontier Lab XYZ,
but it's not helping productivity across
your economy. It's not helping your
military industrial complex until you
deploy it into those guys systems. And
that deployment and diffusion is going
to take some time. And by the way,
you're going to have to build a lot of
compute. You're going to have to build a
lot of energy. These things also take
time. So it's not like you know you
reach across some Rubicon and then it's
all over. Now the one way in which I
might be wrong about what I just said is
if you use the frontier super
intelligence
offensively right you say okay we've got
one super powerful model. The US
government who we're talking to about
this is going to use it and they are
going to comprehensively penetrate
everything about Chinese cyerspace and
insert various trap doors, Trojan
horses, you know, things that we can
use. We get our hooks into their
systems. And so now we can disable them
if they start a war in Taiwan. Now we
can their communication system
if we need to. So that offensive use of
kind of the very frontier model might
negate my point about waiting for
diffusion to happen. But of course,
nobody in the debate is saying that.
Nobody is saying, "Oh, we're racing to
the front because then we're going to
use it offensively. They don't admit
that." Seems like it wouldn't be a very
good look. I can't see why any
superpower wouldn't do that, frankly.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. I don't know what the
counterargument is. I was chatting with
someone in your book who I I shame but
certainly
one of the most qualified to speak on
these things and I mean his basic
perspective
was the first to super intelligence. we
need to hope that they're [laughter]
on some level good people and train this
thing
>> right
>> well and like that's that's it like pray
for it which scared the out of me
to be honest I [laughter] mean I was
like man that's the strategy or it's not
even a strategy that is the hope grab
the rosary and throw that into the
rotation my god that's really terrifying
to think China I'm hoping to take a trip
to China. I had a very tough time there
when I was I was at two universities in
1996. It was a pretty unfriendly time
for a lot of good reasons, but to be an
American there in 1996 with a shaved
head looking like I do.
But I have friends all over the place
and I'm hoping to actually maybe
interview technologists, not just in
China. I mean, there are other places
that are of interest to me, but before
it gets too hot geopolitically, if we're
trending that direction,
>> I think that's a great idea, by the way.
I mean, I think what I found was the
cognitive dissonance of visiting a
company like Hike Vision, which is under
US sanctions
>> and walking around their premises, which
kind of feel very American. It feels
like a cool tech company doing cool
stuff, building cool gadgets. you know
they have a display of they build this
AI enabled camera technology or sensor
technology and so one application might
be you can point this camera at water
and judge the pollution level
>> and because of this you can have an
internal market in pollution control. So
the downstream city which is receiving
water from the upstream city pays the
upstream city to keep the water clean
and that market can exist because you
can precisely measure the pollution
level thanks to this AI sensor which
Hike Vision is building. So you're
thinking, "Wa, this is cool." And then
as you're walking around the building,
they're saying, "Okay, well, we can go
through the atrium now because the
toddlers have gone because, you know,
the crash for the kids of the employees
finishes at 5:00 p.m. And so then there
are all these 2-year-olds running around
and it's a bit of a zoo. So if it was 5,
we wouldn't go through there. But now
it's 6 p.m., so we can." And you're
thinking, "Whoa." Okay, so they've got,
you know, the interests of their
employees at heart. They're building
this anti-polution technology. It's
great. and then you realize they're
under US sanctioned and considered to be
a threat to the US. So it's quite
interesting to process all that
>> in the process of doing research for
this book
and also the broad exposure that you
have to investors. But let's just say
over the last handful of years, who are
some of the most interesting or unusual
compelling is the word I'm searching for
investors who you've had the chance to
meet, talk to, read about, get
acquainted with directly or indirectly.
>> Wow. So many. I mean, I'd say that Bill
Gurley from Benchmark, you know, is
right up there. I always think of the
investment he did in Uber as the
absolute quintessential perfect venture
investment
>> in the sense that he had done the open
table investment and of course open
table is a two-sided marketplace where
you have lots of consumers that are
looking for restaurants, lots of
restaurants. You put tech in between
which creates information and then the
person looking for the place to eat can
precisely say I would like you know Thai
food at this price range in this area
for three people at this time. Ding.
What used to take you a lot of searching
around. Bang it's done. And so Bill
having done that was thinking well
what's another two-sided marketplace?
And he thought well there are lots of
cars and lots of people who need a ride
and you put information in the middle in
the same way. there ought to be
something which is like an app for ride
sharing.
>> And so he imagined Uber way before Uber
existed. That was point number one.
Point number two, he went to see various
entrepreneurs who were in this space and
he checked them out and he had the
discipline not to invest in them
[clears throat]
>> because although they were kind of going
at the right thing, there was some hair
on the deal, some wrinkle, some way they
were approaching it that just felt like
it wasn't going to be quite right. So he
resisted.
Uber came to him before Travis was the
CEO
>> and Bill said, "I'm not doing that."
Because he didn't think the CEO at the
time had what it took. And then there
was an internal switch at at Uber.
Travis became the leader. Bill meets him
and like bang, he immediately invests
because he's been waiting and waiting
and waiting for the idea to be paired.
As you were saying earlier, you have to
have the the market to be paired with
the right person. and he saw it and then
he invested and he was a great board
member and it all went perfectly right.
But then there is this kind of
Shakespearean tragedy in the latter part
of the story where the growth investors
come in. He gets diluted. He no longer
has influence. His key card to get into
the building is deactivated and he's
basically stiffed and he watches, you
know, Uber kind of go off the rails. And
then finally comes, you know, the the
denum where he rounds up the dissident
investors and they have this coup
against Travis and that sets the company
on a path to where they hide Darra and
do the IPO. I just think that's the
ultimate venture capital story and Bill
is the ultimate venture capitalist.
>> He is practically a neighbor here for
me. I'm sure
>> in Austin and we've had a couple of
conversations on the podcast and he's I
would say on a very parallel track to
you with respect to China, right? And he
catches some flack for it. People are
like, "He's an agent of the CCP." I'm
like, "No, trust me, Bill is not an
agent of the CCP. [laughter]
It's just the most ridiculous
>> accusation." But he is a very incisive
observant
human
>> who also happens to be a polymath in
multiple disciplines who can speak
casually about very technical things.
And this also you you referring to Bill
in this way or describing him in this
way makes me think about multiple points
in the infinity machine and I'm pulling
from memory which is as we know pretty
faulty but you know Elia with the
transformer architecture and the
prepared mind I think Demis also just
thinking about a problem deeply and
seriously or with great imagination for
a long time and then when the solution
or the the germ of a solution appears
immediately recognizing it, right? It's
just it's wild to see how frequently
that recurs. Any other investors, you
know, a name that doesn't get much
airplay who
[laughter]
I I think is just a fantastic character
and maybe you could introduce him to
people who are listening if they don't
recognize it. Luke Nosk, where does Luke
>> who has I wish I knew how to turn on my
batteries in the same way to [laughter]
to get the energy that Luke does. But
how does Luke fit into the story of
deep mind and I I suppose more broadly
speaking for that because of that AI.
>> Luke Nosek is this tremendously puppyish
enthusiast, right? and he was a you know
early early part of the PayPal team with
Max Levchin and Peter Teal and he went
through that journey and then Peter
exited PayPal set up founders fund. This
is now I think 2005
and Luke Nosek becomes one of the first
partners and pretty early on he makes
the right judgment on Elon and SpaceX.
>> Mhm.
>> And Luke is the kind of guy who is just
all in. When he falls in love with an
idea and a founder, there is no curbing
his enthusiasm.
And so he's like all in all in all in on
SpaceX. And I think, you know, he
persuaded Founders Fund to like raise a
new fund, put extra money in, like more
more more more more capital in there.
[clears throat]
>> And of course, that paid off massively.
>> And off the back of that, you know, roll
forward to 2010.
>> He's trying to look for the next Elon
Musk. And he does a few kind of frontier
bets. And then along comes Demesis Abis
who is out on the west coast from London
raising capital for this idea of an AI
company which he's going to call Deep
Mind. And you know most people think
that's nuts. This AI remember in 2010
cannot even recognize a photo of a cat.
It can't do anything. We're in deep deep
AI winter. Who would back a company like
that? The answer is Luke Nosac. and he
falls in love with Demis who is a very
winsome character, super articulate,
super relatable and a genius. You know,
he has all the kind of outlier
characteristics you want in an
entrepreneur. You know, the sort of
junior chess champion, second best
player in the world, but also five times
wins the mind games olympiad where you
have to run between boards playing bat
gammon, chess, go and a couple of other
games kind of almost simultaneously. I
mean just kind of crazy crazy smart
obsessed since he was 17 with the idea
of building powerful AI. So Peter Thiel
said to me about Demis I think
individuals tend to have one company
inside them if they're missionary
entrepreneurs they've got one thing they
need to do and for Demis it was to build
AGI like that was what he was fixated by
and the company was downstream of his
desire to build AGI. If he could have
done that at a university, he would have
been happy to do that. But he couldn't
do it at university. So he had to found
a company to do it. And that's the kind
of missionary commitment that venture
capitalists often look for because a
missionary will never quit. No matter
how hard it is, they will keep working.
And so Luke Nosek and Peter Teal jointly
recognize this. Peter is, you know,
contrarian, cynical, aloof, and so is
kind of into it, but at the same time
arms length. Luke is like got both his
arms around Demis is giving him this
bear hug and will not let go. And you
know, Demis says, "I'm not going to move
to California. I'm going to do this
company in London." And Peter and the
other Founders Fund partners are like,
"London? Where is that?" It's kind of
like Somalia or something. I mean,
that's just off the map. And Luke says,
"No, no, no, no. We have to do this. We
have to do this. I will fly to London
for the board meetings and we've just
got to do this deep mind investment."
And so he was the kind of unbridled
enthusiast who got Founders Fund across
the line. And the rest is history. You
know, they put the series A money in.
Unbelievably, it was 2 million at a 4
million valuation. So they got half the
company for 2 million bucks. Not bad.
>> Not bad.
>> And they rode that investment. What a
remarkable story. I really feel like
Luke,
who's also here in Austin, deserves
a lot more credit than he gets. Not that
he's seeking it, right? He's not he's
not out there looking for it, but he is
very good at
riding winners when he is high
conviction, right? which in the venture
game
>> I mean in a lot of investing it's you
can't die you can't run out of bankroll
at the table right you need to have
enough of a portfolio approach to
sustain yourself through periods of bad
luck but if you're systematic it's
riding your winners and doubling and
tripling and quadrupling down and he is
so good at that he is just incredibly
good
>> and as John Duro likes to Hey, the great
thing about venture capital is you can
only lose one times your money.
>> So it's not like a short position for a
hedge fund trader where you can like
really lose a lot, right? So
>> exactly
>> in that sense you're not going to die.
So you can shoot for the moon.
>> So I do have a question. I should know
the answer to this but I don't.
So long ago, this is probably 200 2008.
This is a long time ago actually. I
wonder if I had exposure to deep mind. I
invested in Founders Fund. This was a
very, very long time ago. But what I did
not realize internally, and I'll just
read a couple of my highlights. It is
absurd how many highlights I have from
the Infinity Machine and all of your
books. [laughter]
So, a gap opened up between Teal and
Nok. As a general matter, Teal doubted
that going on boards was a good use of
partners' time. Startups should be left
to sink or swim. The art of venture
capital, he liked to say, was to back
contrarian ideas, not coach company
founders. Just we could spend a lot of
time just on that, but I'm going to move
on. Most venture partnerships decide on
investments by voting. If a handful of
partners see hair on the deal, the deal
will be rejected. But Teal had taken the
unusual position, the collective
decision-making should be avoided. The
way he saw things, if investments were
chosen based on voting, the founders
fund portfolio would consist of
middle-of the road startups to which
nobody objected. And then dot dot dot,
this comes back to the power law, right?
Given that all the profits in venture
come from a few improbable moonshots,
this sort of consensus portfolio would
deliver mediocre performance. So, and
I'll just paraphrase now, Teal empowered
the partners to go allin with their
guts/intuition.
My question is, how is that governed in
any way? Of course, if anyone gave 10
out of 10 conviction and then lost money
consistently, they would presumably be
sort of removed from the partnership or
they'd lose their ability to lead with
that type of gut conviction. But do you
have any idea how that was handled
internally?
>> Yeah. in terms of stress testing ideas,
pushing people to really put their ass
on the on the line for these types of
high conviction but certainly very much
outlier investments. Do you have any
idea?
>> I think internally founders fund was
very torn about the deep mind investment
and I described some of this in the book
where you know they do the first deal
and that's fine. It's $2 million.
>> Mhm. But then you get to series B and
series C and the check size gets bigger
and so the other partners are asking
tougher questions and they're saying,
"Well, wait, is there going to be a
product?"
>> Mhm.
>> And Demis said to me, you know, that his
attitude was, "What do you mean is there
a product? I'm talking about artificial
general intelligence. It's going to make
all products like revolutionized or
obsolete or whatever. And you want to
ask me what the widget is? Give me a
break." you know the [clears throat]
it's all of the widgets they're all
going to be changed and if you're asking
me this question you don't get what AGI
means
>> and so Deis was very frustrated by the
other partners at Founders Fund and I
think internal within Founders Fund
there was a lot of fighting between Luke
who remained enthusiastic and committed
about Demis partly because he was the
guy who would go to London and meet with
him and sit in the board meetings and he
would get the sort of you know several
thousand vaults of Demis enthusias ASM,
you know, injected into his spine at
every meeting and he would come back
buzzing with excitement. And the other
Founders Fund partners who didn't have
that benefit were skeptical. And so Luke
would often come to Demis and say,
"We've got your back. We've got your
back. We know we're going to do the next
round. We're going to lead the next
round." And then actually in series C,
Founders Fund at the last minute pulled
out and they put money in, but they did
not lead.
>> Mhm. And so the answer to your question
is there was a lot of argument within
founders fund as the check size grew it
was harder to have that you know double
down on your winners kind of attitude.
>> Yeah in this case the fish that got away
although I mean it was a fantastic
multiple on their initial money. It
strikes me in reading the book that
I would argue that Demis made absolutely
the right decision with
the Google acquisition. I mean you
mentioned also in the book how he got
criticized in some UK media for like oh
you know giant mega corporation in the
US gets our prized talent cheap kind of
stuff. But looking back, I mean, he
seems to have anticipated
the costs and compute and and just
raw materials that would be required to
do what he was trying to do,
>> right?
>> Would you read that the same way?
>> Yeah. I mean, I often have this debate
with people in London where they say
exactly as you put it, you know, this
was a tragedy for UK tech. great
champion of deep tech, you know, is
bought out cheaply by Google. And I say,
listen, it wasn't cheap. The acquisition
price might have been $650 million,
which was a bit cheap, but you know how
much they put in in terms of recession
development funds over the next 10
years? It was approaching 10 billion,
almost a billion a year, right? So, this
was not selling cheap to the Americans.
This was a cunning British trick to get
a billion dollars of American R&D money
into London per year for the next
decade. terrific win. And by the way,
today there are spinouts from Deep Mind
in London because the talent stayed in
London. And these spinouts are raising
billions of dollars to do new AI
companies. So it's terrific for the
London ecosystem around King's Cross
which is this sort of cool center for
tech in London where you can get the
train in one direction and be in
Cambridge which has quite a lot of good
startups you know in one hour or you can
get the train in the other direction and
be in Paris where there's you know MR
and so forth and it's kind of very wired
into different bits of Europe. So how
long does it take to get from San
Francisco to Mountain View depending on
the traffic right can be well over an
hour. So I think there is a technology
ecosystem which is by no means the
equivalent of Silicon Valley yet, but
it's certainly unrecognizably better
than it was 10 or 20 years ago.
>> What do you think the UK or Europe could
do? Let's let's focus on the UK perhaps
could do to increase the level of
innovation early stage
startup founding etc. Right? Because
looking back at the power law and
certainly just having spent so much time
in California, there's a lot that went
into Silicon Valley, right? And there
are certain things that don't get a lot
of airplay, but for instance, the
difficulty of enforcing non-compete
agreements in California, right, really
led to this sort of roundroin of talent
moving and cross-pollinating like little
hummingbirds of engineering talent and
so on, which [snorts] may not be
replicable depending on where you are,
but what what could the UK do in your
mind if if you had the ear and they were
like, "All right, Sebastian,
tell us what to do.
>> A couple of things. I mean, I think the
mistake that people in Europe make and
Britain as part of this is to believe
that there's some kind of cultural magic
about Silicon Valley where whatever it
is that they're drinking in the water
out there makes them think that failure
is a learning experience which is kind
of weird and the Europeans say, "Well,
we're never going to be like that." And
it's impossible for us to become as
entrepreneurial as Silicon Valley. And I
remind people that when Fairchild
Semiconductor was founded in 1957, the
eight scientists who left the Shockley
lab were called, get this, the
traitorous eight.
>> So good.
>> Traitorous. Why? Because it was
considered treachery at the time to
leave one company and go to another
company. There was no entrepreneurial
culture in the 1950s on the West Coast
in the US, right? The classic business
book of the time was organization man
about people who joined one company and
stayed in it for their whole life and
retired with a gold watch on their 60th
birthday. Right? So you can create an
entrepreneurial culture and that is
happening bit by bit in Britain and
certainly in Israel and it's happened in
China and it's not some magic which is
confined to Silicon Valley. Okay, I it's
worth making that point as the first
thing. Now there are specific policy
shifts that you need to do to make an
ecosystem work and I think you put your
finger on one which is the mobility of
talent is super important. You can think
of a startup ecosystem as something
which circulates three elements money,
people and ideas and you circulate those
and you combine them in different ways.
And each time you combine them, that's a
new company. And each has a shot on
goal. And most of them fail. But all of
a sudden, if you circulate these these
components fast enough, you do get
product market fit. And then you get
these 10x plus returns. Now, in Britain,
when you raise a new round, a series B
say, and you've got like nine months of
runway to build to the next stage from
your company, and you identify the three
key talent that you're going to bring
into the company and make it happen, and
then they turn around to you and say,
"Well, I can come in 6 months." That's a
death sentence, right? That's horrible.
We call it gardening leave in Britain.
That is an appalling idea. We got to get
rid of those gardens and we got to let
people move fast. Another thing is tech
transfer out of universities. In the US
there's the BOL act. There are these
very sophisticated tech transfer offices
which are generous to the entrepreneur
in terms of not demanding too much flesh
>> as somebody exits and that's essential
for making the startup work. In Europe
the attitude is oh we're the university.
We deserve a lot of skin in the game
here. we want 50% of the upside. Well,
in that case, the startup will never
happen.
>> Mhm.
>> And I say to these Europeans, look, go
visit Stanford. They're very generous to
their entrepreneurs. They seem to be
okay financially [laughter]
because if you help the entrepreneur,
you know, you'll get the donations
later. It's all good.
>> Yeah.
>> And so, I think those are just two
things
>> which started a long time ago in the US,
right? You you look at the origins of
Janentech and so on. I mean it's just
been
>> it's it's the genesis of so many not
just companies but industries
effectively in the US.
>> Yeah.
>> Do you think Demis would have built Deep
Mind if he had not read Enders Game?
[laughter]
>> That's a great story. That's a great
question.
>> Can I just tell the Enders game story to
begin with?
>> And also a bit of trivia for folks. I
believe, and not not to like make this
more more difficult, but that when Mark
Zuckerberg first had a profile on
Facebook, the only book listed was also
Enders Game.
>> Oh, I didn't know that.
>> I believe that's true.
>> That's fascinating.
>> So, hop into it with Demis and Enders
Game. So right at the beginning of my
interviewing of Demis we were having the
second meeting which was a dinner and he
told me to read a couple of books before
we had the dinner and one of them was
Enders Game.
>> What were the others just before you
continue?
>> It was a book by David Deutsch called
The Fabric of Reality.
>> Uhhuh. Light read. [laughter]
>> Yeah. Now, I read Enders Game as a
result, and I hadn't read it before. And
as I was reading it, I was thinking to
myself, okay, so this is a story about a
sort of boy hero who saves the entirety
of humanity from an invasion of the
planet by the space aliens. Is Demis
telling me that that's how he sees
himself? That he's like saving all of
humanity with AI?
because it'd be a bit much to believe
that, but it would be even more to have
the tmerity to tell the guy who's
writing a book about you [laughter]
that that's how you see yourself. Like
most people wouldn't expose themsel in
that way. I thought, is Deis really
thinking this? So then I go to have the
dinner and he says, "I hope you read
Enders game because that's really how I
see myself." And I gave the book to my
wife so she could read it so she could
understand me better because I really
identify with Ender. Yeah, it's wild.
>> It's wild.
>> It's a great book. I mean, I haven't
read it in decades, but it is it is a
fantastic read as I remember it.
>> Yeah. I mean, reading it, I must say, as
a mature adult, I thought it was not
that well written.
>> Yeah.
>> But the idea of it is good. And I can
see why
>> the idea is sticky.
>> Absolutely. You know, this image of this
kid who sacrifices everything to
dedicate himself to the craft of
fighting the aliens.
>> Mhm. and you know withstands ridicule
and bullying from his peers and fights
back. It's an appealing image and that's
what hooked Demis. But to answer your
question of earlier, you know, he would
have done AI anyway because he read
Enders Game actually when he was already
kind of around 30.
>> Mhm.
>> And he'd had unbelievably the
determination to build super
intelligence from when he was about 17.
I mean that is wild as well. I mean the
early conviction is just extraordinary.
Did he ask you to read Good Echerbach
an eternal golden braid? I will admit to
you I think Dustin Moskavitz
also a lot of technologists very very
very good technologists recommend this
book
>> or cite it as part of their own journey
to building something incredible. I
think I'm too dumb to read that book. I
had so much trouble. I've had so much
trouble. I've tried two times and yet
I've still not finished that book. I
don't know. Hey, do you have any
recommendations to somebody who's maybe
lacking a few IQ points cuz he was born
on Long Island as to how to navigate
that book? I have to admit I was told by
Demis that this meant a huge amount to
him that he'd read it in his late teens
and that was when he really became
convinced that he could build AI because
the argument in the book is that you
know whatever the human brain can do
computers will be able to do one day
that the human brain operates on ones
and zeros and therefore if you could
build big enough compute you should be
able to replicate the intelligence of
human brains and and that was the sort
of insight that got him hooked on the
idea. So I went off and I tried to read
it. I would say I got like 150 pages in
and got bogged down. I mean it is
[snorts] a difficult challenging read
but at least I kind of extracted the
essence
>> that meant something to my subject to
Demis. You know who would be great for
helping me to understand this? LLM
[laughter]
going to give that a shot and see if
explain this to a sixth grader maybe or
a s or explain it to a six-year-old
maybe even better. Couple of questions
and then we'll start to lay on the plan.
If you had to write another book on a
figure in the world of AI, they could be
relatively unknown
or they could be incredibly known. Who
would that person be? Demis is off the
table.
>> I might want to take Sam off the table
just to make it
>> a little more interesting. Who would it
be if Sam's off the table and Deis is of
course off the table?
>> Well, I guess Dario.
>> Yeah,
>> I think even if you left Sam on the
table, it would be Dario. I mean, I
think he's just a fascinating
fascinating figure as well as being the
current leader
>> of anthropic for people who don't
recognize the name.
>> Yeah,
>> man. You know, I'm working on a blog
post right now. It's about disruption
due to AI and how it's not three years
in the future. It's not one year in the
future. These are book sales across my
entire book catalog and it's not limited
to print. This is all format. Okay? So,
I'll give you some numbers and then I
want you to tell me what happened to
initiate this. Okay. 2022 stasis pretty
consistent. My book royalties are an
annuity predictable.
2023 minus 5%. 2024 minus 13%. 2025
minus 46%.
And 2026 so far on track to be at least
57%.
What happened at the end of 2022?
[laughter]
>> Chat GPT [clears throat]
>> GPT 3.5.
It's just wild. It's really, really
wild. I mean, this stuff is coming fast.
And I really flip and flop. I feel like
I waffled perhaps too much between these
two. I I go from the very I would say
moderate well-reasoned
positioning of Benedict and I agree with
so many of his points to believing that
all of this is just coming so much
faster than anyone can even comprehend
due to the sort of recursive
self-improvement. For the record, I
think that it is much bigger than
mobile, much bigger than internet. This
is so general cognitive capability which
can span you know any human task. I
think the niggle is simply how long does
diffusion take.
>> Yeah. Right. And just to give an example
of that you know I invest in quite a few
biotech companies and
other sciences and if you look at say
alpha fold right I mean absolutely
merited a Nobel prize. We didn't mention
that about demis but it's one thing to
design molecules it's quite another to
deliver it to target tissue right so
like the deliverability of that sort of
a metaphor for AI in a way [laughter]
it's like okay great we have this
pristine perfect molecule how do you get
it to the right place and at the same
time an investor in a company called
Laya Laya Sciences and what they're
doing is producing
a proprietary data set by automating wet
labs using AI, right? And I'm going to
simplify it, right? But they have
gigantic wet labs where they can run in
parallel thousands of experiments that
from the very first step of hypothesis
generation through to the end of the
scientific method is all run
autonomously by AI. And I bring this
particular example up because even I
want to say 6 months ago, 12 months ago,
like they are producing discoveries that
are really non-trivial, right? It's like
it's already happening now. Like this is
not
>> this is not a year in the future. Like
this is happening now. So when you flash
forward to think about
the potential exponential improvement
and I I still to be honest sometimes
when people talk about like exponents
exponents humans aren't good at thinking
exponentially. I'm like yes that's true
but outside of more laws why would AI
capabilities or LLM parameters or
however you want to measure it
automatically improve in exponents. I
don't I don't actually quite understand
that. But once we get to the sort of
recursive self-improvement, it's like,
okay, I can see how that starts to
approach a vertical wall.
>> I agree with you. I think one one
experience from writing the book is
simply that when you're close to the
people inside the labs and, you know, I
wasn't just Demis. I interviewed, you
know, hundred of these AI insiders, you
realize that the stuff in the pipeline
is enormous.
>> Yeah.
>> I think there's a kind of popular
misconception which is there is this
thing called AI and it kind of happened
when Chatty PT came out. So now we've
got it and we're kind of getting used to
it and that's in the rearview mirror.
No, no, no, no. This thing is changing
the whole time as anybody who looks
closely knows. And if you think back,
the progression is wild. You know, you
get this system in end of 2022 which
hallucinates non-stop. Then you plug in
GPT4 16 months later, whatever it was,
and the hallucination radically reduces.
Then it goes multimodal, so it can do
video and audio. And in the meantime,
it's got a very long context window, so
you can plug in an entire TL story novel
and ask questions about it. Then it
starts to do the reasoning stuff and can
do logic and math. Then it becomes
agentic.
Then it's like coding for you. And all
of these changes are packed into three
and a half years. And I agree with you.
I think the next three and a half years
are going to be even more wild.
>> Yeah.
>> So I think there's a big gap between the
inside and the outside view of this.
>> Yeah. That's where these comparisons to
the industrial revolution just
completely fall apart [laughter] on so
many levels. I have one or two remaining
questions for you.
>> The billboard question. I ask this a
lot. It can be a fun one.
>> If you could put anything on a
billboard, metaphorically speaking for
millions, billions of people to see.
Could be anything. image quote question
preferably not commercial. [laughter]
What would it be? What might it be?
>> So a billboard which lots of people are
going to see. I would put prepare your
mind.
>> This is a saying which is originally
Louis Pastor I think the scientist
who said chance favors the prepared
mind. If you're ready for things, you
can make the most of the opportunity
that comes your way. And the amazing
thing about this saying is that it's
come up randomly in different contexts
in different books I've done. So when I
was writing about venture capital, Excel
Capital
>> and one of the founders, Arthur
Patterson, used this phrase as a
description of how he wanted Excel to
invest. that they would run these kind
of scenario exercises where they would
think, okay, there's a new technology
coming down the pike. What kind of
company needs to be built to make the
most of that new platform? What type of
entrepreneur is going to fit this
opportunity? What should we be expecting
so that the person walks into the office
into the conference room and pitches to
us, we already know 90% of what he says
because we've prepared our minds. And
that way we can make a good judgment and
a fast judgment if it's a competitive
situation. So I kind of wrote about the
prepared mind in the context of venture
capital. And then I'm doing the infinity
machine and I'm interviewing Ilia
Satskaver from OpenAI and I'm asking him
why was it you who understood the
significance of the transformer
architecture when it came out
immediately like on the day it was up on
the website you read it. You ran down
the corridor. You went to see your
collaborator Alec Radford and you said,
"We're going to build a language model
on top of this architecture."
>> Well, not only that, he said, "Stop
everything you're doing."
>> Right. Right. Right.
>> And do this. [laughter]
>> Yeah. This vision of the kind of, you
know, overcaffeinated charismatic
seizing on the engineer and saying,
"Drop it, whatever you're doing." And,
you know, in his answer was prepared
mind that he'd been thinking about how
you model sequential data ever since his
PhD in Canada. And when he saw the
solution, this was what he'd been
waiting for for like a decade. And so he
could jump on it. And then when you
start thinking about prepared mind, you
know, you would probably remember this
better than I do, but wasn't there a um
Seattle Seahawks Super Bowl final
against the New England Patriots where
the New England quarterback like does an
interception in the last second of play
and clinches the victory. And when he's
asked after the play, how did you know
to make that run? Where did you how did
you know where the quarterback was going
to throw the ball? The answer was
prepared mind. Basically, he didn't use
that phrase, but you know, in training,
they had studied
the play that the Seattle Seahawks were
going to make. And they knew that given
a certain formation when the ball was
snapped back, there was a certain pass
that was coming. So the guy just takes
off and he runs right into where the
ball comes and he catches it and
intercepts and New England wins. And so
that's a prepared mind in sports.
>> Mhm.
>> And the other reason, last thing,
>> yeah,
>> I would put on the billboard prepare
your mind is that for the age of
artificial intelligence, this is what we
need to hear. And this is a serious
point, right? The risk with large
language models is that we just get lazy
and whenever we need to know something,
we just get it to tell us what to think.
That is not the route to happiness or
satisfaction or anything. We need to
continue to do the hard work of
preparing our minds because that's what
makes us people. You know, I think,
therefore I am. And so I think prepare
your mind is entering a time when it
becomes a more important slogan than
ever.
>> How do you do that for yourself? What
guard rails or policies have you
established for your own use of AI?
>> And it makes me also think of going to
the gym, lifting weights, getting in
cardio. You don't have to do that, but
it is beneficial for you on a lot of
levels. And people, some people find it
quite enjoyable, right? And hence they
do that. And I'm wondering
what the equivalent is for knowledge
workers or people who are preparing
their minds and
don't want to become sort of impotent in
the way that people with directions have
mostly become impotent because of Google
maps and other tools like that. Right?
So what do you what do you do for
yourself personally or how are you
thinking about that? The first thing I
think is that the Google Maps analogy is
the wrong one in the sense that it's
fine to offload a very specific mental
task which to most people is a pain in
the neck.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> And let the machine do that for you.
It's not fine to offload all thinking.
Right. The point of offloading something
should be you get to focus your mental
energy more on the other stuff that you
really get satisfaction and meaning
from. And so for me, what that means is
that I'm very happy to use large
language models to learn about the
scientific output of somebody I'm going
to interview next week.
>> Mhm. All of these AI papers are on
archive and the model has ingested all
of them and the model is extremely good
at telling me okay the scientist you're
seeing next week has these three papers
and the progression between the three
papers is this and this and this and the
comparison with the person you saw two
weeks ago is this and this and this and
you know you learn a lot from the system
like really bootstraps you to learn
faster so that's helping me to think
more not to think less.
>> It's cutting out the time it would take
me to go find all the papers by myself
and then labor through them. It's
cutting to the chase and nourishing me
intellectually.
>> And [clears throat] by the way, I'm not
worried about hallucination because I'm
going to interview the human scientist
anyway. So, I get to cross-check it all.
>> What I would never do is get the AI to
write because frankly, it's not very
good at long form. In fact, it really
sucks. It's fine for writing an email,
although I don't do that either because
I like writing. But it really is I've
tried it once. It's terrible for
anything longer than about 800 words.
But even if it could do it, I don't
think I would ever outsource that
because that's me,
>> right? This is what I do. This is the
thinking process. I think through my
writing, I come to understand what I
understand and think what I think and
believe what I believe through writing.
And I'm not going to give that out.
>> I'm letting out a pensive exhale because
I was thinking of this. A friend said to
me, well, I'll give him credit, Kevin
Rose. At one point, I was I wouldn't say
complaining, observing that AI couldn't
do X or it wasn't very good at Y.
>> He said, when was the last time you
tried that? I was like six months ago.
And he's like, try it again. And so
[laughter]
the rules will become really important
as also the power of these things
increases. And there I want to say it
was the New Yorker. There was a piece in
the New York or it might have been the
New York Times with some very famous I
want to say novelist could have been
Pulitzer Prize winner in literature
somebody at the top and they took three
or four pieces of their own writing had
AI generate three or four pieces of
writing in their voice and gave it to
professional readers
editors and so on and it wasn't clear
people couldn't figure out they claimed
that what he or she wrote was AI
>> how long was the piece of writing
>> I knew that was the question you were
going to ask and I and I don't recall.
So I want to go back and look at that
piece to see. So there was a story
precisely like that from an economist
writer who's very funny and also does
podcasts
>> and he ran that experiment and it was
just as you said you know his friends
who were professional economist
journalists couldn't tell which was the
witty column that he'd written versus
the equally witty ones which the lamb
had generated and he was very pissed off
with this and I look I take your point I
mean for now I can be all complacent and
say yeah I only works for 800 words. It
doesn't work for a whole chapter which
is 20 pages long. But no doubt it'll get
better and better. But I still think I'm
going to cling on to the thing that
makes me me for sure. 100%. And I think
doing the thinking, preparing your mind
in part asking that question, which is
not an easy question, perhaps there's a
different way to phrase it, but like
what what are
the things that make me me? So you don't
accidentally make sacrifices that start
to erode your sense of self but also
sense of selfworth. Right.
>> Preparing your mind. Sebastian,
everybody should check out the infinity
machine. It's it's outstanding. The
infinity machine subtitle deis habis
deep mind and the quest for super
intelligence. And lest people
make the wrong assumption. This is not
here's the latest and greatest in AI. It
is the story of an incredible mind,
a whole cast of kooky and fascinating
characters. It is about a noble quest.
It's about the pitfalls and promises of
entrepreneurship. It contains so many
different levels. And if you want to
also have a basic understanding of what
it is from the ground up that came to be
colloquially referred to as AI or LLMs,
this is a great book for that. It really
lays out kind of the nuts and bolts and
how this evolved over time in a way that
I think is intelligible to
non-engineers. So everybody should check
out the Infinity Machine. Sebastian, is
there anywhere else you would like to
point people or anything else you'd like
to say as we wind to a close?
Well, um,
yeah, you stopped me on that one.
[laughter]
I've enjoyed the conversation. I'm happy
to leave it there. Thank you for doing
it, Tim. It's been great.
>> Absolutely. I'll I'll give one one more
link for folks if they want to find you
on X. That's SC Malib
Malibby. Well, Sebastian, thank you so
much for the time. Really enjoyed the
conversation. And for people listening,
we will include links to everything
we've discussed, all the characters and
everything else at tim.blog/mpodcast.
Just search Sebastian. I'm pretty sure
that Oh, actually, we have Sebastian
Younger. So, there are two Sebastians.
But if you search Malib, M A L L A B Y,
it'll be very easy to find this. And
until next time, be just a bit nicer
than is necessary, a little bit kinder
than is necessary to others, but also to
yourself and prepare your mind. Thanks
for tuning in.